A Guide to the Clifton, Virginia Collection, 1876-1992
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Clifton, Virginia Collection, 1876-1992
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 03-06
0.5 linear feet
The Clifton, Virginia Collection consist of 0.5 linear feet and spans the years 1876-1992. The collection consists of various ephemera detailing the history of Clifton, Virginia including articles, brochures, a program, press release, correspondence, bumper sticker, an account book, photocopies, and posters.
Virginia Room staff
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Room staff artificially created this collection over a period of years. Most of the collection came from unknown donors. The Collier County Museum of Naples, Florida donated the Elijah B. Georgia patent on July 17, 1989. Virginia Beach Public Libraries donated the consolidation materials in March 1992. Phylis Salak donated the William Edward Beckwith 1910-11 “Time Book” on October 16, 2017. The Fairfax County Archives transferred the Town of Clifton “$25 Reward” posters in July 2019.
Historical and Biographical Information
In 1851, the Orange & Alexandria Railroad constructed trackage through the area now known as Clifton and built stations nearby at Sangster’s and Union Mills. During the Civil War, the United States Military Railroad built a siding between the two depots and named it Devereux Station in honor of Superintendent of Railroads John Henry Devereux. A small town grew up around the railroad siding. In 1868, the name changed to Clifton Station and citizens established a Post Office the following year. The Town of Clifton became a weekend resort destination when Harrison G. Otis opened the Clifton Hotel in the 1870s. On March 10, 1902, the State Legislature incorporated the Town of Clifton, which went on to become the largest town in Fairfax County and the first to get electricity and a high school. The Southern Railway closed Clifton Station in 1956, and the town entered a period of decline. Beginning in the 1970s, new arrivals to the area renovated Clifton’s historic buildings and in 1985, the town was listed on the National Register of Historic Places.
Scope and Content
The Clifton, Virginia Collection consist of 0.5 linear feet and spans the years 1876-1992. The collection consists of various ephemera detailing the history of Clifton, Virginia including articles, brochures, a program, press release, correspondence, bumper sticker, an account book, photocopies, and posters. The consolidation materials include a 1961 “Vote for Consolidation” bumper sticker; pro-consolidation literature; and a press release from Anne Wilkins dated May 10, 1961. Brochures include Clifton Home Tours; Buckley’s Inn; Clifton churches; and Anna Sprouse Day. The page from the January 1, 1906 Fairfax Herald newspaper details notable Clifton businessmen including the Buckley Brothers; J.L. Fristoe; A.J. Kidwell; R.C. Hickey; G.B. Wright; W.H. Mathers; S.H. Detwiler; M.M. Payne; J.B. Cross; J.M. Fulmer; R.W. Woodyard; R.M. Kivett; and F.G. Mayhugh. The “Time Book” for William Edward Beckwith (1880-1961), an African-American farmer of Clifton Station, includes financial expenditures and deposits from 1910-1911.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Adair, Annie Elgin (1900-1972); Beckwith, William Edward (1880-1961); Clifton (Va) - History; Clifton Elementary School; Georgia, Elijah B. (1823-1886); Pellettier, Mabel O. (1914-2006); Second Baptist Church, Clifton, VA
Container List
- May Day Program, Clifton Elementary School, May 18, 1957, 1957 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Town of Clifton/County of Fairfax Consolidation materials [bumper sticker, brochure, letter, press release], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- “The Choice For Clifton: Progress or Decay”, 1965 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Annie’s Calendar" - Annie E. Adair, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Brochures, Clifton, VA Home Tours, 1967, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Various brochures of Clifton, VA, Undated, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Newspaper, Fairfax Herald - Clifton Station column, 1906 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- “History of Clifton, Virginia” by Annie E. Adair and Helen E. Buckley, 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
- “The Naming of Clifton, Virginia” by Mabel O. Pellettier, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- “Why Was It Called Clifton?” by Mabel O. Pellettier, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Elijah B. Georgia barrel patent (Clifton, Va.), 1876 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Second Baptist Church, Clifton, VA ledger book, 1926-1942 [photocopied], 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- “Time Book”, William Edward Beckwith (Clifton Station, VA), 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Posters, Town of Clifton “$25 Reward”, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)